<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plasticity</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5Cfeeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>n-onorato.github.io/</id><updated>2019-06-25T12:15:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>A Review of Metro Exodus</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CMetro-Exodus-Review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-25T12:15:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T12:15:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-25:n-onorato.github.io\Metro-Exodus-Review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Metro Exodus is a good game, with great atmosphere and characters. Although it's held together with only nominal gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
    main {
        background-image: url(images/snow.png);
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently finished playing Metro Exodus by 4A Games and I had a good time but wanted to share my thoughts. Like the other Metro games 4A Games continue to capture the atmosphere of a decaying russian world trying to cling to life after a nuclear apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title would suggest the game is centered around an exodus of it's most familiar setting. No longer are you exploring Moscow's underground, instead you're on the surface trying to find a new home. This story is where Metro shines because the gameplay, while engaging, is best described as serviceable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart of the game is its extremely detailed environments, characters, notes, and audio tracks. Considering the 20-24 hour campaign the amount of voice work done is incredible. There are multiple instances where you can sit around for 30 minutes and listen to a scene take place where characters have conversations and develop themselves. Sometimes the dialogue can be somewhat overbearing because I didn't want to listen to 20 minutes of exposition. But that's ok, the dialogue isn't essential, if its not interesting then you can usually leave the encounter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only real weak point is the gameplay, which suffers from a lack of choice. Nearly every engagement starts with stealth. Which has ok mechanics but isn't extremely fun. After playing games like Dishonored and Hitman it's clear that choice makes stealth much more fun. The ability to climb environments, hide bodies, and wear disguises makes the game more fun. These mechanics are sadly missing in Metro Exodus, which seems to push stealth pretty strongly but only allows you to crouch, takedown enemies, and throw objects to distract enemies. This works, but makes each encounter more like a slow simple puzzle of you evading enemies or killing them from a distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often stealth will fail as you'll be found and then you'll kill everyone following the typical FPS pattern of shooting and ducking. One interesting mechanic they aded is that if you do well enemies will give up and put their hands up. You can then knock them out or kill them. This only affects humans, mutants once hostile will usually always attack to the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These combat encounters aren't bad, they are entertaining and fun. But if there were more options during stealth allowing you to change disguises and explore more intricate environments it would be more fun. I don't think the other combat could be made more fun without increasing the difficulty, which is an option as I played on normal but more difficult options exist that make the enemies smarter and force you to be more conservative with your ammo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I would recommend people play the game because the characters are interesting and the story is good. I think 4A games deserves support for the amazing work they do. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Review"></category></entry><entry><title>Kids and Screen Time</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CKids-Screen-Time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-19T10:46:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-19T10:46:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-19:n-onorato.github.io\Kids-Screen-Time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instead of reducing a kids screen time, ensure they socialize, play, and enrich themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Insert a completely original and interesting image of a child looking at a phone or tablet here. It'll be totally interesting to look and a worthwhile introduction to the article&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I use &lt;a href="https://app.getpocket.com/"&gt;pocket&lt;/a&gt;, a service backed by Mozilla that helps me collect articles I want to read from around the internet and store them in one place. It also makes recommendations from articles other people are reading. One of these articles was from Outsideonline.com titled &lt;a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2387461/book-raising-humans-digital-world"&gt;"The Best Book Yet on Parenting Screen Addicted Kids"&lt;/a&gt;. The article is by &lt;a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/1746271/jacob-baynham"&gt;Jacob Baynham&lt;/a&gt; and consists of Baynham reflecting on what the lessons they took away from the book &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0814439799/"&gt;"Raising Humans in a Digital World" by Diana Graber.&lt;/a&gt; First off I'd just like to mention that despite the title of Baynham's article it's not about kids actually dealing with any kind of addiction to technology. Instead it's about how to raise a kid in a world where a harmful amount of time can be spent on screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the article is ok and I'd recommend you give it a read and think for yourself. But there's one large point that bothered me in this article and often bothers me when it comes to this topic. Most discussions around screen time are focused on limiting kids time on a screen. This might seem appropriate but it's not, the fear of screens is that kids will miss out on other more valuable and enriching things. Screen time is only harmful if it reduces other activities like spending time with the family, socializing with friends, or doing other worthwhile tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the article promotes some of the strange ways people try and forcibly reduce screen time. Such as setting technology free zones such as bedrooms or technology free times. Even encouraging fasts from technology for a day or two. I cannot imagine these would be successful strategies as it makes technology a thing to be desired. Something they want but can't have, which makes it all the more valuable. It doesn't seem like a way for kids to learn to use technology responsibly. that being said there's nothing wrong with encouraging kids to track and keep a perspective on how much time they spend using technology. But the focus should be an spending time with your kid and making sure they do other things besides screen time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the article talks about the harms of social media along with screen time which in my opinion overly complicates the article. Screen time is a generalized term and when kids are on it some level of parental control should be used. The discussion of social media is a separate more complicated issue. It would've been better to not touch on that or to write a separate article talking about how kids should be introduced and encouraged to use social media if they are to use it at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Parenting"></category><category term="Response"></category></entry><entry><title>Life Without Curiosity</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-13:n-onorato.github.io\ImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had access to the entire world. But also imagine it's winter and not all that nice outside. You could venture outside and look around at this new world but would you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I find the answer obvious, of course I would explore this new world. I would ask why things had changed, am I intended to leave the house now or has there been a mistake? Initially, I think I would explore the world due to fear. I would want to know if my peaceful, stable life was coming to and end or was under threat by a bulldozer outside my door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If after investigating the outside and determining there was no threat and observed things carrying on as normal, would I still choose to go outside? This is where the idea of curiosity comes in. What would propel me to explore the world? Is curiosity simply a sense and desire to understand the world for it's own sake? Maybe curiosity only exists because we want to respond to threats, if we understand them we can usually mitigate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way I think this is an interesting question and encourage you to think about it yourself. (:&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry><entry><title>Discovering Arkane</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CArkane-Studios-Is-Cool.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-11T11:38:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T11:38:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-11:n-onorato.github.io\Arkane-Studios-Is-Cool.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I played through Prey (2017) twice and watched my SO play through it once. It's obvious that I love the game and when a game has such an impact I like to examine who made it. As it turns out Arkane Studios, the creator of prey is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I played through Prey (2017) twice and watched my SO play through it once. It's obvious that I love the game and when a game has such an impact I like to examine who made it. As it turns out Arkane Studios, the creator of prey is also the studio behind many other games I've enjoyed such as the games in the Dishonored series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People refer to their games as &lt;a href="https://www.giantbomb.com/immersive-sim/3015-5700/"&gt;immersive sims&lt;/a&gt; which define the goals of the game. Typically these games emphasize variety in choice, story telling, and interaction. One reason I love Arkane's games is the varety of their world building. Here's a list of all the ways they build up a world from the top of my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text logs found throughout the world, ranging from stories, poems, and any other things that might be written down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio logs which are usually used for story exposition but also character building and things like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common conversations between NPCs can often be interesting and give interesting info about the world of their disposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall environment also tells a lot about the world. Including things like graffiti and NPCs routine animations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One area Arkane Studios hasn't explored too deeply is in the area of video. This makes sense as it's more work and if things change it's easier to re-record some audio or change some text. But I do remember them included 2 stylized "found footage" videos in Prey which added a fun sense of depth to the info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that being immersive sims are just a style of game. The real success is in Arkane being able to design and execute that style with a compelling story and refined gameplay. If you haven't played Dishonored or Prey I would suggest giving them a shot. Even if you're like myself, and haven't enjoyed other immersive sims such as Bioshock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I would be remiss if I didn't mention Arkane Studios has recently announced their next project titled "Deathloop" which seems to revolve around two characters stuck in a sort of groundhogs day situation and the only way to end it is to kill the other. I'm very much looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Arkane Studios"></category></entry><entry><title>Your brain is fine using GPS</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CGPS-Wont-Rot-Your-Brain.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-07T11:33:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T11:33:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-07:n-onorato.github.io\GPS-Wont-Rot-Your-Brain.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
    [data-title="your-brain-is-fine-using-gps"] {
        margin-bottom: -10px;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, The Washington Post published an article written by M.R. O'Connor, titled &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/ditch-the-gps-its-ruining-your-brain/2019/06/05/29a3170e-87af-11e9-98c1-e945ae5db8fb_story.html"&gt;Ditch the GPS. It's Ruining your Brain.&lt;/a&gt; and as someone with a neuroscience background this caught my attention. Plenty of activities such as video games and social media were said to rot and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
    [data-title="your-brain-is-fine-using-gps"] {
        margin-bottom: -10px;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, The Washington Post published an article written by M.R. O'Connor, titled &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/ditch-the-gps-its-ruining-your-brain/2019/06/05/29a3170e-87af-11e9-98c1-e945ae5db8fb_story.html"&gt;Ditch the GPS. It's Ruining your Brain.&lt;/a&gt; and as someone with a neuroscience background this caught my attention. Plenty of activities such as video games and social media were said to rot and ruin your brain and that's never been the case. The brain might change, but outside of damaging it or developing a disease it wont be ruined. The main thrust of the article focuses on the idea that using GPS can decrease hippocampal gray matter and that is related to devoping dieases. O'Connor begins by extolling the usefulness of GPS before diving into how it affects perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people are told which way to turn, it relieves them of the need to create their own routes and remember them. They pay less attention to their surroundings. And neuroscientists can now see that brain behavior changes when people rely on turn-by-turn directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is completely true and not at all surprising. By offloading work to technology we would expect the brain to behave differently simply because it's doing something different than it did before. So far things are fine, but as we see later on O'Connor confuses gray matter volume with overall health and function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies have long shown the hippocampus is highly susceptible to experience. (London’s taxi drivers famously have greater gray-matter volume in the hippocampus as a consequence of memorizing the city’s labyrinthine streets.) Meanwhile, atrophy in that part of the brain is linked to devastating conditions, including post-traumatic stress disorder and Alzheimer’s disease. Stress and depression have been shown to dampen neurogenesis — the growth of new neurons — in the hippocampal circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I think O'Connor gets confused. The hippocampus and the brain in general adapts to the tasks being demanded of it. This is called brain plasticity and it's an important part of learning. Increased hippocampal gray matter in taxi drivers can indicated better navigational performance, but so what? Most people's hippocampi have adapted to their own daily tasks. Not everyone can be a taxi driver in london.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O'Connor also seems to suggest having a small hippocampus is bad by linking it to post-traumatic stress disorder and alzheimer's. This isn't correct, the brain in a disease state might experience pathological changes due to the disease. But atrophy is due to a having a disease is quite different than changes due to brain plasticity. When someone has a disease there is atrophy despite that function still being needed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the study that this article is based on also seemed to suggest a larger hippocampus is better, the lead researcher Véronique Bohbot is quoted...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we are paying attention to our environment, we are stimulating our hippocampus, and a bigger hippocampus seems to be protective against Alzheimer’s disease,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After looking at the study this is a misleading reflection of the research. The research shows that lower hippocampal volume is a risk factor for Alzheimer's but this relationship isn't understood. This isn't evidence that increasing hippocampal volume would protect you from alzheimer's. It's far more likely that whatever environmental, genetic, and behavioral conditions lead to alzheimer's also tend to allow or cause lower hippocampal volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's unfortunate to see these kinds of articles picked up. There's likely an interesting story about what roles the hippocampus plays in navigation and how these differ between individuals. Instead we get throw away articles about GPS rotting your brain from a respected publication. Labeling it with an opinion tag doesn't give The Washington Post a pass either. They are providing a platform and should ensure to the best of their ability that any objective claims made in the article are true.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Science"></category><category term="Response"></category></entry></feed>