<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plasticity - Thoughts</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="n-onorato.github.io/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>n-onorato.github.io/</id><updated>2019-07-17T10:30:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>The Problem of Caffeine!</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/sleep-caffeine-lifestyle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-17T10:30:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T10:30:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-07-17:n-onorato.github.io/sleep-caffeine-lifestyle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most people don't have a healthy sleep schedule, but I don't think it's their fault. Keeping a healthy sleep schedule is hard and society doesn't facilitate good habits. By now most people know good sleep can keep us more alert, reduce stress, and reduce our risk for diseases like heart …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most people don't have a healthy sleep schedule, but I don't think it's their fault. Keeping a healthy sleep schedule is hard and society doesn't facilitate good habits. By now most people know good sleep can keep us more alert, reduce stress, and reduce our risk for diseases like heart disease and diabetes. Unfortunatly the recipe for a good nights sleep is involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll need to...
* Avoid caffeine almost entirely, even small amounts of caffeine can disrupt sleep and it sticks around in your blood for a long time.
* Don't drink or eat before bed, having to get up to pee in the middle of the night disrupts your sleep.
* Sleep in a cool room because it facilitated higher quality sleep and quicker sleep onset.
* Don't interact with screens or strong light sources an hour before bed. This allows melatonin to be released and prepares us for sleep.
* Only sleep and have sex in your bed, no sitting there on your phone or watching TV. This conditions your body that you're about to go to sleep, facilitating the process.
* Go to bed and wake up at consistent times. The bodies circadian rhythm is fairly consistent and should be respected.
* Get regular exercise, this one may or may not directly help but it's a good idea as it keeps your body and brain functional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individually each of these is achievable, but collectively they represents a big change in our habits. Avoiding caffeine is difficult because it's pervasive in society and a lot of products contain it. It's socially acceptable to use coffee as a stimulant throughout the day and even consume it in Sodas later in the day. These drinks are also delicious, Starbucks has some amazing drinks/milkshakes and it's unfortunate that good sleep requires almost completely forgoing these drinks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond just changing our diets, good sleep requires us to keep a longer and more strict bedtime routine than most of us are used to. This starts with cutting off food and drink an hour or two before bed. Followed by an hour of dim-light where our activities are limited to reading, board-games, and whatever else can be done in dim light. Hopefully we have some way of automating a cool room for ourselves otherwise that will need to be done. Then finally we can lay down to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two difficulties with this routine exist. The first is avoiding screen-time, at home we have large TVs, our phones, and computers all calling our for our attention. Everyone likes watching their favorite show at night and probably check any notifications from their phone as it comes in. In fact many people end their day laying in bed looking at their phone, almost he exact opposite of what should be done.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem involves sleeping in a cool room. Most houses built in the united state are insulated buildings with a central air conditioner. Most responsible people are conscious of their energy usage and realize how inefficient it would be to cool their house to sleep comfortably. Unfortunately most houses have no passive cooling technologies, can't target their cooling, and lack small air conditioners installed in a single room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that being said these conditions represent the ideal in terms of sleep quality. They do not all need to be completed before a persons sees a benefit. Even removing screen time 30 minutes before sleep would be helpful and lead to higher quality sleep.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Thoughts"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="sleep"></category></entry><entry><title>Kids and Screen Time</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/Kids-Screen-Time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-19T10:46:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-19T10:46:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-19:n-onorato.github.io/Kids-Screen-Time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instead of reducing a kids screen time, ensure they socialize, play, and enrich themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Insert a completely original and interesting image of a child looking at a phone or tablet here. It'll be totally interesting to look and a worthwhile introduction to the article&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I use &lt;a href="https://app.getpocket.com/"&gt;pocket&lt;/a&gt;, a service backed by Mozilla that helps me collect articles I want to read from around the internet and store them in one place. It also makes recommendations from articles other people are reading. One of these articles was from Outsideonline.com titled &lt;a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2387461/book-raising-humans-digital-world"&gt;"The Best Book Yet on Parenting Screen Addicted Kids"&lt;/a&gt;. The article is by &lt;a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/1746271/jacob-baynham"&gt;Jacob Baynham&lt;/a&gt; and consists of Baynham reflecting on what the lessons they took away from the book &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0814439799/"&gt;"Raising Humans in a Digital World" by Diana Graber.&lt;/a&gt; First off I'd just like to mention that despite the title of Baynham's article it's not about kids actually dealing with any kind of addiction to technology. Instead it's about how to raise a kid in a world where a harmful amount of time can be spent on screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the article is ok and I'd recommend you give it a read and think for yourself. But there's one large point that bothered me in this article and often bothers me when it comes to this topic. Most discussions around screen time are focused on limiting kids time on a screen. This might seem appropriate but it's not, the fear of screens is that kids will miss out on other more valuable and enriching things. Screen time is only harmful if it reduces other activities like spending time with the family, socializing with friends, or doing other worthwhile tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the article promotes some of the strange ways people try and forcibly reduce screen time. Such as setting technology free zones such as bedrooms or technology free times. Even encouraging fasts from technology for a day or two. I cannot imagine these would be successful strategies as it makes technology a thing to be desired. Something they want but can't have, which makes it all the more valuable. It doesn't seem like a way for kids to learn to use technology responsibly. that being said there's nothing wrong with encouraging kids to track and keep a perspective on how much time they spend using technology. But the focus should be an spending time with your kid and making sure they do other things besides screen time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the article talks about the harms of social media along with screen time which in my opinion overly complicates the article. Screen time is a generalized term and when kids are on it some level of parental control should be used. The discussion of social media is a separate more complicated issue. It would've been better to not touch on that or to write a separate article talking about how kids should be introduced and encouraged to use social media if they are to use it at all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Thoughts"></category><category term="Parenting"></category><category term="Response"></category></entry><entry><title>Life Without Curiosity</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/ImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-13:n-onorato.github.io/ImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had access to the entire world. But also imagine it's winter and not all that nice outside. You could venture outside and look around at this new world but would you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I find the answer obvious, of course I would explore this new world. I would ask why things had changed, am I intended to leave the house now or has there been a mistake? Initially, I think I would explore the world due to fear. I would want to know if my peaceful, stable life was coming to and end or was under threat by a bulldozer outside my door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If after investigating the outside and determining there was no threat and observed things carrying on as normal, would I still choose to go outside? This is where the idea of curiosity comes in. What would propel me to explore the world? Is curiosity simply a sense and desire to understand the world for it's own sake? Maybe curiosity only exists because we want to respond to threats, if we understand them we can usually mitigate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way I think this is an interesting question and encourage you to think about it yourself. (:&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Thoughts"></category><category term="philosophy"></category></entry></feed>