<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Plasticity - Thoughts</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5Cfeeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>n-onorato.github.io/</id><updated>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Life Without Curiosity</title><link href="n-onorato.github.io%5CImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-13T12:20:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Nicholas Onorato</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-13:n-onorato.github.io\ImStuckInaWellandThatsOk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you've spent your entire life in a house with no windows or doors to the outside world. All your needs were taken care of, people stopped by mysteriously, food was delivered, and things magically got cleaned. Then imagine after living years like this the door opened, and you had access to the entire world. But also imagine it's winter and not all that nice outside. You could venture outside and look around at this new world but would you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I find the answer obvious, of course I would explore this new world. I would ask why things had changed, am I intended to leave the house now or has there been a mistake? Initially, I think I would explore the world due to fear. I would want to know if my peaceful, stable life was coming to and end or was under threat by a bulldozer outside my door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If after investigating the outside and determining there was no threat and observed things carrying on as normal, would I still choose to go outside? This is where the idea of curiosity comes in. What would propel me to explore the world? Is curiosity simply a sense and desire to understand the world for it's own sake? Maybe curiosity only exists because we want to respond to threats, if we understand them we can usually mitigate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way I think this is an interesting question and encourage you to think about it yourself. (:&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="philosophy"></category></entry></feed>